What do we know about the future?
ما الذي نعرفه عن المستقبل؟
Difficult question, simple answer: nothing.
سؤال صعب، وجواب بسيط: لاشيء.
We cannot predict the future.
لا نستطيع التنبؤ بالمستقبل.
We only can create a vision of the future, how it might be,
يمكننا فقط وضع تصور حول المستقبل، كيف يمكن أن يكون،
a vision which reveals disruptive ideas, which is inspiring,
نظرة تكشف عن أفكار مشوشة، وملهمة،
and this is the most important reason
وهذا هو السبب الأكثر أهمية
which breaks the chains of common thinking.
الذي يكسر قيود التفكير الشائع.
There are a lot of people
هناك الكثير من الناس
who created their own vision about the future,
الذين يكونون نظرتهم الخاصة حول المستقبل،
for instance, this vision here from the early 20th century.
على سبيل المثال، هذه الرؤية من بدايات القرن العشرين.
It says here that this is the ocean plane of the future.
تقول بأن هذه هي طائرة محيطات المستقبل.
It takes only one and a half days to cross the Atlantic Ocean.
إنها تستغرق يوما ونصف فقط لتقطع المحيط الأطلسي.
Today, we know that this future vision didn't come true.
اليوم، نحن نعرف أن هذه الرؤية المستقبلية لم تتحقق.
So this is our largest airplane which we have,
إذاً هذه أكبر طائرة لدينا،
the Airbus A380, and it's quite huge,
إنها "ايرباص إي 380"، وهي ضخمة جداً،
so a lot of people fit in there
لذلك يمكن وضع الكثير من الناس داخلها
and it's technically completely different
وتقنيتها مختلفة تماماً
than the vision I've shown to you.
عن الرؤية التي أريتكم إياها.
I'm working in a team with Airbus,
أعمل في فريق مع إيرباص،
and we have created our vision
وكوّنا نظرتنا الخاصة
about a more sustainable future of aviation.
حول مستقبل أكثر استدامة للطيران.
So sustainability is quite important for us,
لذا الاستدامة مهمة جداً بالنسبة لنا،
which should incorporate social
والتي يجب أن تشمل القيم الاجتماعية
but as well as environmental and economic values.
فضلاً عن البيئية والاقتصادية.
So we have created a very disruptive structure
لذا أنشأنا بنية مشوشة جدا
which mimics the design of bone, or a skeleton,
تحاكي تصاميم العظام، أو الهيكل العظمي،
which occurs in nature.
التي توجد في الطبيعة.
So that's why it looks maybe a little bit weird,
ولهذا السبب ربما تبدو غريبة قليلاً،
especially to the people who deal with structures in general.
وخاصة بالنسبة للناس الذين يتعاملون مع الهياكل بشكل عام.
But at least it's just a kind of artwork
لكن في النهاية هي فقط نوع من العمل الفني
to explore our ideas about a different future.
لاستكشاف أفكارنا حول مستقبل مختلف.
What are the main customers of the future?
من هم زبائننا الرئيسيون في المستقبل؟
So, we have the old, we have the young,
لدينا الكبير ولدينا الصغير
we have the uprising power of women,
ولدينا القوة الصاعدة للنساء،
and there's one mega-trend which affects all of us.
وهناك اتجاه رئيسي يؤثر علينا جميعاً.
These are the future anthropometrics.
هذا هو مستقبل توقعات علم قياسات الجسم البشري.
So our children are getting larger, but at the same time
أطفالنا يصبجون أكبر، ولكن في نفس الوقت
we are growing into different directions.
نحن نمو في اتجاهات مختلفة.
So what we need is space inside the aircraft,
إذاً ما نحتاجه هو مساحة داخل الطائرة،
inside a very dense area.
داخل منطقة كثيفة جداً.
These people have different needs.
هؤلاء الناس لهم احتياجات مختلفة.
So we see a clear need of active health promotion,
نرى حاجة واضحة لتعزيز الصحة الفعالة،
especially in the case of the old people.
خاصة لدى كبار السن.
We want to be treated as individuals.
نريد أن تتم معاملتنا كأفراد.
We like to be productive throughout the entire travel chain,
نود أن نكون منتجين على طول سلسلة السفر،
and what we are doing in the future is
وما سنفعله في المستقبل هو
we want to use the latest man-machine interface,
أننا نريد أن نستخدم آخر واجهة للإنسان مع الآلة،
and we want to integrate this and show this in one product.
ونريد أن ندمج ذلك ونعرضه في منتج واحد.
So we combined these needs with technology's themes.
لذلك قمنا بدمج كل تلك الاحتياجات في موضوعات تقنية.
So for instance, we are asking ourselves,
على سبيل المثال، نحن نسأل أنفسنا،
how can we create more light?
كيف يمكنا إنشاء ضوء أكثر؟
How can we bring more natural light into the airplane?
كيف يمكننا إحضار ضوء طبيعي أكثر إلى داخل الطائرة؟
So this airplane has no windows anymore, for example.
هذه الطائرة لم تعد تمتلك أية نوافذ على سبيل المثال.
What about the data and communication software
ماذا عن برمجيات البيانات والتواصل؟
which we need in the future?
أيها نحتاج في المستقبل؟
My belief is that the airplane of the future
اعتقادي الشخصي هو أن الطائرة في المستقبل
will get its own consciousness.
سوف يكون لها إدراكها الخاص.
It will be more like a living organism
ستبدو وكأنها كائن حي
than just a collection of very complex technology.
أكثر من كونها تكنولوجيا معقدة جداً.
This will be very different in the future.
هذا سيكون مختلفا جداً في المستقبل.
It will communicate directly
سوف تتصل مباشرة
with the passenger in its environment.
مع الركاب في محيطها.
And then we are talking also about materials,
ثم نتحدث عن المواد،
synthetic biology, for example.
البيولوجيا التركيبية على سبيل المثال.
And my belief is that we will get more and more
وباعتقادي سوف نمتلك موادا جديدة أكثر فأكثر
new materials which we can put into structure later on,
مواد جديدة يمكننا وضعها في الهيكل لاحقاً،
because structure is one of the key issues in aircraft design.
لأن الهيكل في واحد من القضايا الرئيسية في تصميم الطائرة.
So let's compare the old world with the new world.
لذا دعونا نقارن العالم القديم مع العالم الجديد.
I just want to show you here what we are doing today.
أريد أن أريكم هنا فقط ماذا نفعل اليوم.
It takes a lot of weight,
تأخذ الكثير من الوزن،
and it follows the classical design rules.
وتتبع قواعد التصميم الكلاسيكية.
This here is an equal bracket for the same purpose.
وهنا جزء مساو لنفس الهدف.
It follows the design of bone.
إنه يتبع تصميم العظام.
The design process is completely different.
عملية التصميم مختلفة تماماً.
At the one hand, we have 1.2 kilos,
من جهة، لدينا 1.2 كيلو،
and at the other hand 0.6 kilos.
ومن جهة ثانية لدينا 0.6 كيلو.
So this technology, 3D printing, and new design rules
لذا فهذه التقنية والطباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد وقواعد التصميم الجديدة
really help us to reduce the weight,
تساعدنا حقاً في نقليل الوزن
which is the biggest issue in aircraft design,
الذي هو من أكبر المشاكل في تصميم الطائرات،
because it's directly linked to greenhouse gas emissions.
لأنه مرتبط مباشرة بانبعاثات غازات الدفيئة.
Push this idea a little bit forward.
ندفع هذه الفكرة قليلاً للأمام.
So how does nature build its components and structures?
كيف تبني الطبيعة مكوناتها وهياكلها؟
So nature is very clever. It puts all the information
الطبيعة ذكية جداً. إنها تضع كل المعلومات
into these small building blocks, which we call DNA.
في وحدات البناء الصغيرة هذه، التي تسمى بالحمض النووي
And nature builds large skeletons out of it.
والطبيعة تبني هياكل كبيرة منها.
So we see a bottom-up approach here,
إذاً نرى هنا أسلوبا بناء من القاعدة للقمة،
because all the information, as I said, are inside the DNA.
لأن كل المعلومات، كما قلت، موجودة داخل الحمض النووي.
And this is combined with a top-down approach,
وبدمج هذا مع مقاربة القمة نحو القاعدة،
because what we are doing in our daily life
لأن ما نفعله في حياتنا اليومية
is we train our muscles, we train our skeleton,
هو أننا ندرب عضلاتنا، وندرب هياكلنا،
and it's getting stronger.
لتصبح أقوى.
And the same approach can be applied to technology as well.
ونفس الأسلوب يمكن تطبيقه على التكنلوجيا كذلك.
So our building block is carbon nanotubes, for example,
لذا فوحدات البناء لدينا هي أنابيب الكربون النانوية، على سبيل المثال،
to create a large, rivet-less skeleton at the end of the day.
لبناء هيكل كبير وبدون مسامير في النهاية.
How this looks in particular, you can show it here.
كيف يظهر هذا عملياً، يمكن أن تروا ذلك هنا.
So imagine you have carbon nanotubes growing
تصور أنه لديك أنابيب كربونية تنمو
inside a 3D printer,
داخل طابعة ثلاثية الأبعاد،
and they are embedded inside a matrix of plastic,
وهي مضمنة داخل شبكة بلاستيكية،
and follow the forces which occur in your component.
وتتبع القوى الموجود في مكونك.
And you've got trillions of them.
ولديك ثرليونات منها.
So you really align them to wood,
وهكذا تقوم بمحاذاتها حقا بالخشب،
and you take this wood and make morphological optimization,
وتأخذ هذا الخشب وتجري التحسينات الشكلية،
so you make structures, sub-structures,
بحيث تصنع بنى وبنى فرعية،
which allows you to transmit electrical energy or data.
تمكنك من نقل الطاقة الكهربائية أو البيانات.
And now we take this material, combine this
والآن نأخذ هذه المواد، وندمج هذا
with a top-down approach,
مع مقاربة القمة نحو القاعدة،
and build bigger and bigger components.
ونبني مكونات أكبر فأكبر.
So how might the airplane of the future look?
إذا كيف يجب أن تبدو الطائرة في المستقبل؟
So we have very different seats which adapt
لدينا مقاعد مختلفة جداً تتكيف
to the shape of the future passenger,
مع حالة الراكب المستقبلي،
with the different anthropometrics.
مع قياسات بشرية مختلفة.
We have social areas inside the aircraft
لدينا أماكن اجتماعية داخل الطائرة
which might turn into a place
والتي يمكن أن يتم تحويلها إلى مكان
where you can play virtual golf.
حيث يمكنك أن تلعب الغولف الافتراضي.
And finally, this bionic structure,
وأخيراً، هذه البنية ذات الأعضاء الآلية،
which is covered by a transparent
المغطاة بغطاء البوليمر الحيوي الشفاف
biopolymer membrane, will really change radically
سوف تغير جذرياً
how we look at aircrafts in the future.
كيف ننظر إلى الطائرات في المستقبل.
So as Jason Silva said,
وكما قال جايسون سيلفا،
if we can imagine it, why not make it so?
إن أمكننا تخيله، فلم لا نصنعه أيضاً؟
See you in the future. Thank you.
أراكم في المستقبل. شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)